Mastering market structure is one of the
best things that you can do for your
technical analysis. When you're moving
with the trend, it's easy to make money.
When you're moving against it, you will
be consistently killed by the market.
Now, I've used market structure as the
core concept of my trading systems since
I first found profitability about 6
years ago now, and it's awesome, but
it's pretty easy to get wrong. So, in
this class, I'm going to teach you
everything you need to know about market
structure so that you can trade it
successfully and you don't end up
catching falling knives, fighting the
market, and getting killed by moving
against the trend. So, let's get into
the basics. Markets move in three main
phases. Uptrends, downtrends, and
consolidations.
An uptrend is simply a phase where the
market is moving up. Downtrend, where
the market is moving down, prices are
getting lower. And a consolidation is
where the market moves sideways. And if
we averaged it out, basically price
wouldn't have made any movement to the
upside or the downside. Now these three
phases are going to be the phases of
which we are trading. We are going to
buy during uptrends and we are not going
to sell. We are going to sell during
downtrends and we are not going to buy.
And when it comes to consolidations, we
are pretty much just going to avoid
these. We don't really want to trade
consolidations because there's no clear
direction as to whether the market is
likely to go up or go down. And the idea
is we just want to move with an uptrend
for the duration of the trend and
eventually the market will give us
signals that it is moving back. And when
it starts to show us that it might be
moving down, we stop buying and we
actually start to sell instead. So these
are the three core phases that you need
to understand. Uptrends, consolidations,
and downtrends. Uptrends are for buying.
Downtrends are for selling. And
consolidation is for sitting out of the
market or finding opportunities
somewhere else. When it comes to
identifying whether a market is in an
uptrend or a downtrend, there is, in my
opinion, a clear-cut and correct way to
do this. Now, we don't want to use
things like trend lines. I know a lot of
traders believe a trend line indicates
the direction of the market. But the
problem with trend lines is actually
what you can see just here where
sometimes a trend line will break
indicating to trend line traders or
trend traders as a whole that the market
is likely to move down but then it
actually just continues moving up. Now
when you think about it realistically a
trend line is just an arbitrary line
that you've drawn on the chart and it's
not really giving you any clear insight
into real price action. So instead of
using tools like trend lines, we're
actually going to look at the real price
structure, which means when we're
looking at a market, we want to view the
highs and the lows, and they indicate
which way the market is going. So it's
the most realistic, the most raw way of
looking at which way the market is
heading. To do this, we use concepts we
call high and low structure, which is
essentially what you can see on the
chart here. Higher highs and higher lows
indicate an uptrend. So where you can
see I've written hh this is a higher
high and this is simply a high that is
higher than the previous one. Okay. So
as you can see we are continually
forming higher highs in the price
structure here. Obviously this is an
example but you'll see this on a real
chart in a moment which tells us that
this market is endlessly moving to the
upside. It keeps going higher therefore
indicating an uptrend. Now in order to
maintain the uptrend we also have higher
lows and this is showing that price
structure each low like this one is
higher than the previous one and this
one here again is higher than the
previous one. Now this is how we
validate the continuation of the trend
because the higher highs are obviously
what leads us into profitable moves if
we're buying the uptrend. But the higher
lows essentially protect the integrity
of the trend. Providing the market
continues to make higher lows, then this
market should indeed continue moving
higher. And the idea for us as traders,
which we're going to get into soon, is
to buy around these higher low points to
catch these larger moves. The reason
higher lows are important to kind of
protect the integrity of the trend is
because what can happen is that the
market can come down like this and push
through a higher low. Now, this would
then create a lower low. Okay? Because
this low that we've just formulated at
this level is now lower than the
previous low which was indeed a higher
low over the previous lows. Right? So
keeping it simple there. Essentially
this low is lower than the last one
which tells us that the integrity of
this uptrend is now broken because the
market is showing willingness to push
lower than previous lows that were
printed in the market. So what would
this lead into then? Well, generally
what we see after the formation of a
lower low is the start of a downtrend.
So this lower low might then be followed
and often will be followed with a lower
high. Okay? So we can mark that as an
LH. This lower high is simply a high
that is of course lower than the
previous one which is this one just
here. This tells us that the market is
actually now starting to trend
downwards. And instead of moving up and
instead of looking to buy because we're
expecting it to move up, we would now
shift the narrative. And what we would
hope to do is see a pullback or
retracement as that's also called to
sell in and around the next lower high.
We're expecting from this point onwards
for new lower highs to form and for the
market to continue moving down. So that
is kind of how we see trends using highs
and lows and the simple price action way
to view the changes in the trend. Now
let's lock in on this phase of price
action on Euro Swiss Frank. This works
on all markets on all time frames. We're
going to go through that high low
structure and mark out this trend. So
from where we are going to begin, we're
looking at pretty much this high and
then our swing low of the entire
movement is going to be down here and
then our swing high of where price
currently is is up here. So we're going
to work out the trending direction
between this area of price action. So
the first thing we can do is just use
this path tool to start plotting the
trend. We have our high here. We have a
low. However, one thing I want to draw
your attention to is this low did not
push beneath a previous higher low. So,
this phase of price action following to
this move and then down to here is
actually just consolidation. Okay?
Because we didn't break through a higher
low. The higher low being this one just
here initially, we haven't yet validated
or changed the trend at all. So, this
would be a consolidation. Now we can
then see there was a push down here.
This pushed us through into a lower low.
So this is actually the beginning of a
downtrending phase of price action here.
Okay. Now from this lower low, the
market comes up and creates a high.
Guess what? This high is lower than the
previous high. So this would be our
lower high. The market then comes all
the way down very quickly to this level
and prints a lower low. Okay. So now
let's mark those on. We have a lower
high which is lower than the previous.
Now we do also have a lower high just
here which was then validated with the
breaking structure that appeared. And
then we have our lower low once again.
So we can see that each of these lows
and each of these highs is lower than
the previous ones that the market
printed. So we can remove this for now
and just focus on that structure. Okay,
I'm going to mark this as well. We have
a high,
then we have a lower high, lower low,
lower high. Note how we didn't mark this
low. It's because it's not a lower low.
This low was lower. So, this is actually
still a higher low until we break this
point, which creates the downtrend. So,
following on from this lower low, what
we actually see from the market is a
push to the upside just here where this
high is actually higher than the
previous. So this is a higher high or
once again a kind of transformation
point for the market where we're
shifting from moving down to now
potentially moving up. So in real time
this would be your validation or your
kind of confirming factor to tell you
instead of looking to sell this market
you might now want to start looking to
buy. We can then see from that point on
using the path tool. So our new trend
looks like this low to high. Then we
come in and we create a low here. We
don't actually make a break all the way
through until this point. Then we come
back down and we create a low around
these points which is then followed by a
push up which pretty much takes us to
where we are now. So to plot this trend
out, we can see there is now a higher
low which is higher than the previous
low. We then see there is another higher
low printed around here. And we can see
that there is a higher high printed at
just this level when the market made its
drive through the highs just there
creating a high that was higher than the
previous one. So now let's take a look
at what this looks like on the chart.
We're going to run through it with the
path tool so you see the full
explanation. From the high down to the
low is essentially the major first move.
This is where we created our first
downtrending price action. But to really
refine it in, we have this consolidation
followed by this push down which creates
a lower high and validates it with a
lower low. The market then comes and
creates a lower high, pushes down,
validates it with a lower low. The
market then pushes up to create a higher
high, pulls back down to validate it
with a higher low. Then we have this run
to create a higher high, which is higher
than this previous one. Then we come in
to create a higher low and push up to
create a new higher high as well. Okay,
so that is the overall refined view of
the trending market and this is a market
that's shifted from downtrend into
uptrend and you can see both of the
directions there and both of the trends
laid on that. Now, one question you
might have of course because you can see
I've averaged out the price action here
is why aren't we accounting for this
area for example as lows? And that is
because of course this did not create a
new higher high. So essentially any
price action that takes place underneath
this high is then just consolidation
again. We've created our low at this
point. We created our high at this
point. So anywhere between these two red
lines is sideways price action. It's
only when the market breaks out above
this high that we actually validate this
higher low and can then start looking at
new higher lows and higher highs. Okay.
So, if we don't create a new higher
high, then the higher low is not going
to be valid. Meaning, basically, this is
the lowest point we reached before we
broke through here. Therefore, this is
going to be our higher low. If the
market had pushed up like this and then
pulled back and then pushed to this
level, then this would indeed be our
higher low. But for the given example
we're looking at, we like to average out
and see things for just the simple
individual highs and lows, which in this
case is going to look like this. Okay?
And then on the downtrending move, we
have consolidation move. But then this
is where our trend begins with our high
down to our lower low, then to our lower
high, then to our lower low. So that's
an idea of structure mapped on a real
chart. Obviously, as you can see, it's
not as clean as a diagram, but this is
what you're going to be working with. So
we are going to look at a fair few chart
examples throughout this class. So you
can see this in real markets, as well
as, of course, the diagrams and
explanations we give. So let's move on.
All right. So the next thing to talk
about is impulses versus corrections.
Impulses and corrections are the two
phases of which markets trade in when
they are in a trend. So during an
uptrend, which is going to be pretty
much all of the price action from the
low here up to the very high in the
trend. There are going to be two types
of move in each of these little pushes.
We get impulse moves and correction
moves. An impulse move is the protrend
move, which essentially means it's the
move that creates a higher high or in a
downtrending scenario, it's the move
that creates a lower low. So the impulse
moves actually decide the trend
direction. Right? If we get a push from
here down to here and it pushes through
a higher low creating a lower low,
that's actually an impulsive move which
is now deciding the direction of the
trend. Now with this next move again as
well we have this lower high down to our
lower low and as you can see this move
pushed us through a previous low. So
that makes it an impulse move right. So
the impulsive moves are essentially the
movements that push price over highs or
beneath lows. We can see here we have a
high then the pullback then the impulse
move is the one that pushes us to a new
high. So, an impulse move will push us
past this level and that's going to
create the new protrend movement
essentially. So, the impulses mapped out
on this chart are pretty much all of the
ones we have now marked along with this
one here. These ones, so 1 2 3 4 are
bullish impulses and they are pushing us
into new highs confirming the existence
of an uptrend. For the bearish impulses,
we are looking at this one and this one
because this one here pushes us from a
high down to a low which is lower than
the previous low crafting that lower low
therefore breaking us through a low
becoming an impulsive move. So the
impulsive move basically determine the
downtrend here and then following
impulsive moves will continue the
downtrend. Now, if the market created
this low and then had a push all the way
back up like this, which pushed us over
this lower high once again and actually
created a higher high, then this move
would be the impulse move to a new
uptrend. Okay, so that's impulses. The
second type of movement is corrections
or corrective moves. Corrections are the
pullback moves. So, a pullback is
essentially where the market is slowing
down temporarily and making a movement.
uh kind of against the overall trend.
Now this happens because of course
buying is very strong in these impulsive
moves but people are going to take
profits. Some people are going to sell.
So we get this kind of alleviation for
the market where weakness comes in for
the short term until we see a price
where traders are happy to buy in mass
again. Then we get that new impulse. So
corrective moves are basically contained
within the high and the low of each of
the impulsive moves. You can see the low
of the impulsive move is there. The high
is there. The corrective move does not
break above a high and it does not break
beneath a low. All it does is pulls back
inside of the range of the larger
impulsive move. So you can see that's
what's happening with every single one
of these corrective moves. Okay. So a
corrective move is basically counter
trend if we are in an uptrend here
overall. So this averaged out is going
to be a pretty clear uptrend. Let me
mark that on. We know the impulsive
moves are therefore going to be up or
protrend moves and the corrections are
actually going to be going down. So they
counter the overall idea. Okay, they are
essentially retracements or pullbacks or
phases where the market is going in the
opposite direction to the overall bigger
trend. Now in the downtrend where we
have bearish impulses or downtrending
impulses which are continuing to push
the market lower, the corrective moves
are going to be pulls back to the
upside. So any short sellers who are
profiting from sell moves are going to
buy back their contracts which is how
they close them to take a profit. That's
going to inject small amounts of buying
pressure into markets around uh new lows
which will create these corrective moves
pulling back. So we call it a
correction, a pullback or a retracement
either or any of those. And then when we
reach our new lower high point then we
will follow through with a new uh
impulsive move. Okay. So impulse moves
are protrend and corrective moves are
counter trend. Okay. And it's important
to understand these phases because we
are always going to be looking as to
whether the market is continuing to make
bullish impulses or whether it breaks
into bearish impulses. Now, if we track
the impulse moves, that is how we
determine whether the market's making
new highs in an uptrend or whether it's
breaking down into new lows in a
downtrend or once again whether it's
going to be breaking from a downtrend
into an uptrend by making a new bullish
impulse. So, it's important to
understand the concept of impulse and
corrections. Now, another use case of
these impulse corrective moves is these
corrections which in the uptrend are
going to be pulls to the downside are
actually where we want to buy. Now, if
we want to buy a market that is
continually moving up, it's ideal for us
to be able to buy as low as possible
because, of course, the lower price we
can get in at, the more profit we can
make when the market moves to higher
prices. So, what we don't really want to
do in an uptrend is end up buying up
here. Okay? We don't want to buy at
these levels. We want to buy as low as
physically possible in each of the
moves. So, if we see the market push up
like this and it creates a new high,
rather than buying here, we want to
ideally be able to buy somewhere in the
corrective move. That way, not only do
we profit on all of the movement that
happens above this level, but we can
actually profit on all of the price
movement that happens as price
reapproaches a previous higher high.
Okay? So, we get the biggest profit
potential by buying from the corrective
points or the corrective moves in an
uptrend. And the same goes for a
downtrend. If we can sell around the
high of the corrective move, then we get
the biggest profit on a short trade,
which is basically where you profit when
the market falls by getting in here and
managing to catch the entirety or the
majority of the downward impulsive moves
that then occur. So now we've popped
back over to our Euro Swiss Frank
example, and we're going to mark the
impulses and corrections on this chart.
We're going to start with the impulsive
movements on this phase of price action
from the very beginning. So we have a
low here which has then pushed up and
it's pushed us over the previous
structural highs. So from here to here
is our first impulse. Okay. Then we can
see the market pulled back. However, it
failed to break through the low. So
therefore this is going to be a
corrective move. So let's mark them
different colors based on the trend.
Green that's going to be our impulse.
red. That's our correction. Then we have
another push to the upside here,
creating a new high ever so slightly.
That is going to be our impulsive move.
And then the market comes back and
creates a bearish corrective move. Why
is this a correction again? Because it
didn't break us through any significant
lows. In order to change the trend, we
would have needed to see a break of this
low here. Okay? So then we get another
impulse to the upside from this low to
this high. That's going to be an
impulsive move or a protrend move. Now,
this is where things get a little bit
messier, and this is good to show you.
This move here, although it did
eventually follow through into a lower
low, in real time, would have been seen
as a corrective move because, of course,
we can't see that the market was going
to move into a downtrend. So, we would
essentially be looking at buying this
level in anticipation of the market then
moving higher. Then what we actually saw
from that point was that the market
didn't push higher. It ended up pulling
back here. So this move realistically is
just going to be seen as a consolidation
move. And that goes for basically both
of those pushes there. From this point
to around here, the market didn't get
anywhere. It just failed to make a new
low, failed to make a new high. So this
is a consolidation or a phase of price
action that we would generally want to
not trade. Now, we then do get, however,
from this high down to this low, an
impulsive move. And this one can be
classified as an impulsive move because
it broke through a previous low. Right?
We see we had this low marked up just
here. This low was broken with this move
down. So, that creates a new bearish
impulse or basically makes this push
down a bearish impulsive move or a
downtrend impulse. So, that would then
lead us to kind of shift the narrative.
We're not looking at bullish impulses
and bearish corrections anymore. We're
looking at the impulses to be the large
down moves and the corrections now
become the shorter pullback moves. So
this would be our corrective move. So
what we can do is make this one green.
So you can see this is an impulse. Our
next correction would then be up to this
point. Our next impulse would be down to
the low just here. But then we have a
pretty immediate market shift. So from
this low up to this high is also an
impulse. And the reason that this one is
an impulse is because it has created a
high which is higher than the previous
high. Okay. So we have impulse
correction impulse correction impulse.
That's an uptrend. We move into a bit of
a messy phase of consolidation. But then
we make an impulse starting a downtrend
correction impulse continuing the
downtrend. But then we are immediately
followed by another impulse which pushes
us back into new highs therefore
validating a new uptrend. So the next
corrective move is going to be a bearish
corrective move which is the pull down
from the high that we've just marked
down into this low. This is our
correction because the market is now
actually moving to the upside. It's
bullish. Okay. So our next impulse will
then be from this low to the formation
of a new high which is going to be this
piece of price action here. So that's
going to be our impulse. Then we have a
correction corrective move down to this
low followed once again by an impulse
which pushes us higher. Okay. So that's
a view of the impulses and corrections
on a real chart. You can see that the
market is initially bullish. So the
impulses are making new highs. Then we
have an impulse move that makes a new
low which makes the market bearish or
downtrend. Then we have an impulse
pretty quickly that pushes us back into
the uptrend and the market phase
continues from there of continually
making higher highs and higher lows. So
let's plot this on real quick. We have
pretty much from this point onwards that
is an uptrend. Okay, so this phase is
uptrend. We then have from this low up
to this high which is also going to be
an uptrend.
So let's make these green as well just
so that we are very clear on that.
Then we have the consolidation which is
pretty much nothing happens at this
phase. We're going to leave that gray to
indicate no direction. And then from the
high that we print pretty much there
down to the low just there. We're going
to mark that out as a downtrend because
that is where the market was shifting to
the downside. So now you can see how
we've formulated the market direction by
using high low structure and then we've
also plotted them as impulse
corrections. So you can see what that
would look like. Now I know this is
rather messy. Don't worry, your analysis
is not going to be this messy. I'm
plotting this on to show you the theory.
Okay, we keep it simplified when we get
down to some chart examples in a bit.
Okay, so we've been through high low
structure. We've been through uptrends,
downtrends, consolidations. We've talked
about impulses and corrections. Now
let's talk about break of structure or
BOS. Now a break of structure is simply
a tool or pretty much a markup that we
use to determine where the trend has
broken. So a break of structure is
pretty much every time a new high or low
is broken, we envision that as a boss or
a break of structure. It's simply
because the structure has now broken in
one direction or the other. Okay. So we
have the high printed here. When the
market comes up and prints a new high,
that creates a break of structure. And
the break of structure takes place at
the previous high. Pretty much at this
point here where the market pushes
through. Okay? So that would be a break
of structure. We also see another
breakup structure here when the market
pushes through the previous high. Why do
we call it a break of structure? Well,
because the existing structure is
breaking into a new high or a new low.
Right now, we use this BOS tool to kind
of simplify and envision where the
breaks are happening to keep us in line
with the trend. You'll see later in the
video how we use this to create
confirmations and formulate real trades.
Now, I indicate breaks of structure both
ways. There's also something that people
use called a change of character. So,
it's actually called uh a chalk or a ch
or something like that. In my eyes, this
is nonsense terminology and I'm not
going to use that. So, if you've used
that before, uh I just call it a breaker
structure just so you don't get confused
through the video. If you haven't, you
can use it if you want, but I just
prefer to view things as what they are.
So, I mark then the level here where the
market pushes from higher highs and
higher lows into its first lower low as
again a break of structure. What we've
actually seen now though is a reversal
break where the market initially these
breaks of structure or BOS's were
bullish. We were seeing bullish breaks
into new highs. Now we've seen a bearish
break of the structure into a new low.
So this BOS here indicates a trend
reversal. Now as you can see this high
where our break of structure could
potentially take place if the market
pushed higher. It doesn't take place.
Okay? We don't get a break of structure
there. Instead, what we get is a push
through the next low, which then again
creates the next break of structure or
in this term creates a bearish impulse
and validates continuation of the
downward trend. So, breaks of structure
are essentially taking place at the
points where highs are breaking into new
highs or where lows are breaking into
new lows. And these things are going to
be pretty much how we indicate which
direction the market is going. We're
going to use them for trade
confirmations and just making the
analysis clearer. you're going to see
these a lot more. But that is what a
breaker structure is. And some people
will call this one a chalk ch of
character, whatever. I don't do that. If
you do, you can continue to. But
throughout this video, you're going to
see this indicated as breaks of
structure instead of that. Okay. So,
let's move on. So, in a simplified
manner now, we're going to run through
this little phase of price action on
Australia dollar, Japanese yen, and mark
out these breaks of structure. So, we're
going to begin around here. We have a
high pushed down to create a low, a
lower high, and now we've pushed down to
create a lower low. Now, until we break
this high, we are not really changing
the trend direction because of course
the market could pull up to pretty much
here, but still keep moving down. The
reason for this is the market here did
not make a new low. So, this is still
our valid low and anything that happens
between basically this level and these
levels here is just consolidation. So
this entire move becomes a consolidative
move. So what we would do to approach
this is mark our BOS line on around this
high. We can just put it there just to
keep it nice and simple. And then we
would have a BOS line that we could mark
out here. If the market was to push
through this low, that would create a
break of structure upon the push through
which would continue the bearish move.
But what we did instead in this example
was push to the upside which at this
level where we start to close above the
previous high creates our first BOS. So
the valid breaker structure or BOS is
this one here. There's no break here. So
there is no BOS there. From that point
onwards we created a new high. We then
came down created a new low and we
pushed up to this point which created
once again a new high. So at that point
we see a clear BOS. We see our high
printed there. We can drag that across
and you can see the structure being this
high has broken into a new high. Okay,
so that's going to be our next BOS. Now,
at this point, our valid low is this
level. So, we've got two opportunities
from pretty much this point onwards in
price action. Either number one, we
create a new low, push higher,
indicating a break of structure and
continuation of the uptrend. Obviously,
you can see that is what happened. But
the alternative would have been if the
market had pushed down, crushing through
this level would have created a BOS here
and that would have indicated further
downside or the start of potentially a
downtrend which could push us into
bearish impulses. Okay. Now obviously as
you can see with the benefit of
hindsight here this market pushed into a
new high creating a break of structure
at this level here as the market pushed
its way into a new high. So what this
does again is now creates our valid low.
This is our higher low. We know that
because the market's gone and closed
higher. So this would be our BOS point,
right? If the market was able to push
through this level, that would indicate
a downward trend. What we see happened
is we pushed up, we pushed down, we
stopped there, we pushed up and created
a new high. So what we've got now is a
new higher low, which we can pretty much
put in around this point just here. So
from this point up to here, that's going
to be our break of structure at this
level. And now again, we've created two
levels to work with. Either we push up,
pull back, and then push up again,
creating a new high, or we come and push
down and break through this low, which
would indicate a downtrend beginning.
Okay. So from where we are, which is
here, we now see the markets pushed up.
It did come down to break through this
low, but it only broke with a wick. And
we're going to get into this very soon.
I want to just briefly mention it now,
but if you see a wick like this, we
don't really use this as a valid closure
or a valid change in the trend. Now, a
wick, the little sticks coming off the
candles, what that indicates is
rejection of price action. It's the
candle bodies or the big blue and gray
blocks that you're seeing that indicate
confirmation. So, if we wick under a
level like this, that's not necessarily
telling us that this market is going to
be moving to the downside immediately.
Sure, the fact the market got down here
could be indication that maybe the trend
changes soon, but it's not really going
to validate a change in the trend until
we see confirmation with closures. So,
following this push lower, we then have
a push higher which pushes us over our
previous high. However, once again,
these are just wicks. So pretty much
from this low all the way up to this
high, we now have a little phase of kind
of no man's land where we haven't closed
above, we haven't closed below. What
we've just done is create a wick beneath
and a wick above. So that actually puts
this bit of phase of price action from
here through to here into what we call a
consolidation. And until the market made
a closure one way or the other, we
wouldn't have validation as to whether
the market is going to continue moving
up or whether it's going to start moving
down. Now, at this point, obviously
here, we created a break and close. And
that went underneath our previous low.
So, just clean this up a little bit. Our
previous low that we had marked was
pretty much these levels here. And as
you can see, this push created closures
beneath that level. So therefore, this
would become our BOS or break of
structure because we've seen closures
underneath the level. And this is maybe
first indication that the market is now
moving in a downtrend, which as we can
see is kind of what it's doing cuz it's
pushed us through to the next lows as
well. So by marking the BOS's and
marking the swing highs and lows and
waiting for a breakup structure either
way, we basically get validation of
whether a trend is going to continue
going up, continue going down or reverse
to the other direction. Here we had our
first break which came in at this level
here that indicated an uptrend where we
had bullish impulse, bearish correction,
bullish impulse, bearish correction,
bullish impulse, bearish correction.
Then we shifted into consolidation. The
market did nothing but eventually it
broke through. What's this break? Well,
this considering it's now broken through
a lower low has become a bearish
impulse. So now we could look for
bullish correction, bearish impulse and
so on and so on and so on. That would be
the first indication that this trend
could potentially be changing direction.
So that is how we plot BOS on the chart.
And really it's just for number one
confirming trend directions. Number two
keeping our structure analysis pretty
neat. As you can see this compared to
what we did before with drawing the
impulses and drawing the HHL structure
on the chart. It was a bit of a mess.
But this is very simple and easy to work
with. We can see from this point onwards
if the structure breaks here we go up.
If it breaks here we go down. If it
breaks here we go up. If it breaks here
we go down etc etc. And it gives us a
clear way to understand which way the
market is going and a clear way to react
to the breaks in structure that we may
see whether they are up protrend or down
counter trend and the start of a new
trend. So now we've taken you from no
understanding of structure through to
understanding impulses, corrections, how
to determine uptrends and downtrends by
using high and low price structure, and
how to identify and indicate breaks of
structure, which will either continue
moving the market higher or lower or
indicate reversals, as we see here. From
this point, you've pretty much got
everything you need to build the
foundation of a profitable market
structure trading strategy. Now, we're
going to talk about some traps and
nuances and mistakes that people make
before going on to showing you how to
profitably trade using the structure
theories we've discussed so far. So, the
first big mistake that a lot of traders
make with structure is getting the
internal structure wrong. Right? Now,
internal structure is anything that
takes place inside of basically one of
these impulsive moves. So, our impulse
in this example is from this low up to
this high. Anything that takes place
under this high and above this low is
called internal structure. So the market
can do whatever it wants unless it
breaks out one side or the other. There
is no real shift or no real urgency for
us to start looking for positions. And
any trades we do take are going to be
kind of lower probability because
they're not moving with the larger
trend. Now the mistake that people make
in regards to internal structure is they
will see a high forms and then we get a
little low which is internal. we get a
new lower high also internal and then
when the market breaks through this low
for example traders will then see this
here as a break of structure and a
confirmation of this market going lower.
So they will start looking for selling
opportunities thinking because the
structure has broken here we've actually
seen a change in this upward trend. Now
you may already be able to see the
problem with this and that is because
with it being internal structure we
still have a clearly intact uptrend. We
had an impulse. We had a correction. We
had an impulse. And now anything that
happens here, whether it does all of
this crazy price action on a lower time
frame is still just a corrective move.
And the market can then still and
probably will still go and push up in
line with the larger uptrend. So if you
start selling after an internal break
here, let's say you sell from this high
when the market pulls back. Well, what
can easily happen is that the market
just pushes through into its next
impulsive move and you end up getting
killed on the sell because you've sold
into a market that hasn't actually
indicated a break in structure at all.
Now, what we could see which would make
this better would be if the market had
pushed up like this and created a new
higher high, okay, at this level. Well,
then that would have number one created
a break of structure here indicating a
new impulsive move which would then have
created this price action of impulse
correction impulse and then if the
market had pushed down through this low
that would be indeed a break of
structure which would be a bearish
impulse. So we would be well within our
right mind to sell from here on out
because we will have actually seen a
clear break of structure where bullish
impulses are breaking into bearish
impulses. But when you start to see the
market like this and you treat this as a
valid breaking structure, well now
you've got a problem because this here
is not a higher high. All it is is a
piece of internal structure that really
doesn't tell us much of the story. And
if you start selling into that, well
then when the market breaks up to make a
new impulse, you're going to lose and
you're going to be confused of why it
happened. But hopefully not now that
I've explained that. So making sure you
don't get caught up in the internal
structure and make sure you're only
working off of the clear high low
structure of the market is a very simple
way to avoid one of the biggest traps
and biggest mistakes people make with
structure. Right now, I want to show you
that on a chart because I think this is
going to resonate with a lot of people
who have been into structure trading
before or currently and are struggling.
So, if you take a look at this chart
here, we've seen a break of structure
which has taken place over the previous
highs. This being the break and this
being what some people will see as a
higher high. So, seeing this price
action on the chart, a lot of people are
going to look for buys when the market
pulls back. So they might look for the
retracement with the expectation to then
continue buying this because they see
well this has broken structure which has
pushed us into an uptrend. Okay, you can
see that there is on the surface a break
of structure here over this high and
over this high. Now the problem with
this is there is actually no clear break
of structure here. Although it looks
like there is, it's a bit of an illusion
because if we look at the low that's
been printed by price which has taken
place down here, we can now see that
realistically everything that happens
above this low is just internal
structure. If we look at our impulsive
move, it begins here and it runs all the
way down to here. There is then nothing
which has indicated a new break and
change in the structure. So until we
push over this high, there is no change
in the trend. And all this is is a
corrective move that is likely to then
follow through with a new impulse. So
although it looks like when you look at
this structure, we see, okay, we've had
a break of structure, we're happy to
start buying, realistically, there is no
reason to do that. In fact, if anything,
you should continue selling because
there's been no change in the structure
other than this small kind of internal
structure meaningless pullback move. So,
if you were tricked by this, and I know
a lot of traders are, this is one of the
biggest problems with structure, then
you're going to be drawn into buying
when in reality, what happens is the
market just makes this next impulsive
move and pushes into new lows. So, what
would have fixed this? Well, rather than
creating a low and then just trending up
like this, if we had instead created the
low here, pulled back to these highs,
then created a new low and then pushed
up above the structural highs, that
would be a valid break because we'd have
actually seen the impulses changing
direction. But because we didn't get
that, this is indeed still just a
corrective move and is unlikely to lead
into a large reversal. So therefore
should be approached as just a
correction to sell from into further
bearish impulses.
The next big mistake that people make
with structure, and this one's a really
easy fix, is failing to differentiate
liquidity sweeps to breaks of structure.
Now, a liquidity sweep, we're not going
to go massively in depth on the topic of
liquidity in this video, but there are
many classes on my channel. But a
liquidity sweep is basically where the
market will push above or below a swing
high or low, take out liquidity, which
is essentially orders, and then reverse
sharply in the opposite direction. As we
can see when we look at, of course, the
low we just drew on here, and the high
that we have up here. So, we see a push
beneath the swing low and then a sharp
reversal. We see a push above the swing
high and then a sharp reversal. So
although on the surface these may look
like breaks of structure because the
market has pushed through this level,
it's actually not. It's actually pretty
much the opposite and is very likely to
move against you. So the way you can
differentiate between actual breaks of
structure which are going to lead into
you know new moves and the liquidity
sweeps that are going to lead into sharp
reversals which will kill you is to look
for closures above or below structure.
So we can see at this low we had no
candle closure. And the candle closure
by the way is simply when we see a large
candle body like this close through a
high or low. So if we look at this
previous breaker structure we have a
high low and then the break of structure
which takes place here is a closure. We
see a candle close higher than the
previous high. That is going to indicate
continuation of the trend. When we look
at this potential reversal though we
actually see no closure under this low.
We see a wick instead. Wicks indicate
rejections or rejected and attempted
price action. Bodies indicate confirmed
and closed price action. So if we see
the selling rejected at this level,
what's that telling us? That's telling
us buyers are too strong for sellers to
get down there. So the next likely move
is we go all the way back up and carry
on in the uptrend. So by seeing a wick
here, you know, do not treat this as a
break of structure. This is instead a
liquidity sweep. The simple rule you can
follow is if there is no candle closure
above the level, don't buy. If there's
no candle closure beneath the level,
don't sell. Don't expect that to lead
into a new trend. You have to see
closures such as we validated the breaks
here when we started to see candle
closures at this area over here. Okay,
that would be fine. But until we get a
closure, as long as it's just wicks,
treat it as either consolidation or no
confirmation of reversal. So we can see
again after we pushed above this high,
no closure, no closure, and then the
market went for a sharp reversal. If
we'd have seen a candle body close above
this level, that would have then
indicated that we can start buying
pullbacks. But because we didn't get the
closure because we only got the wick, we
see this as a sweep of liquidity or a
sweep of the high and low instead of a
closure and confirmation of continued
trend. So make sure you're waiting for
candle closures and not trusting wicks.
because if you trust a wick as a break
of structure, you're going to get killed
a lot of the time. So, we've discussed
pretty much everything there is to talk
about in regards to structure and now
we're going to learn how to trade it.
And the most simplistic way to trade
with market structure is by introducing
a concept called supply and demand.
Okay. So, what we have here is a diagram
of an uptrending market. We have higher
highs and higher lows. The market is
impulsing to the upside and then there
are bearish corrective moves. Now when
the bearish corrective move bottoms out,
we create here what we call a demand
zone. The demand zone is basically an
area where significant demand has come
into a market or in other words where
significant buying has taken place. Now
when we see a large impulse like this,
this is driven by institutional buying.
Okay, the big push that breaks us into
new highs is basically banks and trading
firms placing significant orders which
is big enough essentially to drive the
market. Okay, the more people that want
to buy, the higher prices go because the
more sellers can demand for the asset.
That's why they go high. So more people
that want to buy is pretty much
equivalent to the demand to buy. So
another way of saying more people want
to buy is saying there's high demand.
Okay, there's a lot of demand for buying
this asset. When we see a corrective
move bottom out, we then see what we
call a demand zone a lot of the time,
which is basically a area where the
market has very temporarily gone
sideways or consolidated before a large
impulse to the upside. This tells us
that this is a good place to buy. And
basically the concept will then be if
this is seen as a good place, good price
level to buy at, when the market returns
to this level again, we are likely to
see more buying taking place. Okay. If
there's a discount and then things get
expensive and then it comes back down to
the discount and you want it, well,
you're probably going to buy it down
there. So, that is what supply and
demand is. Now, this is demand, the buy
side. On the sell side, it works the
exact same way, except what's happening
here is the institutions are injecting
significant amounts of supply into the
market. So, that is why we call it
supply instead of demand. Obviously,
this is then seen as a premium price to
sell. If the market retraces to it and
you want to sell your assets, well, the
more you sell it for, number one, the
more profit you make if you are in a buy
trade. Number two, the better price you
are in at if you are looking to short
the market. Okay, so that's the supply
version. Let's focus on demand for the
moment then. So, what we often see
within the market when we're looking at
candlesticks is we have our demand zone
push away and then the market pulls
back, retests the demand zone, and then
makes its next push away. Now, it's not
always going to come back. Sometimes
it's just going to come to there and
then run away and you'll miss that
trade. But it's the most simplistic and
effective way to trade the trend using
market structure by just looking to buy
demand zones and sell supply zones. So
in this example then following on we had
a demand zone impulse correction retest
of demand zone. This is where we want to
buy. Then following that point we have
had a demand zone impulse. we would now
look for a correction and our demand
zone is where we would want to buy
again. Okay, so we would essentially
approach this market by buying this
level stop-loss beneath the low of the
zone and then we can look to continue
the market higher because we know with
an uptrend intact, it's likely that
we're going to get new highs once again.
Right? So that is the simple supply and
demand way to trade. That's demand for
uptrends. You only want to trade demand
in uptrends and you only want to trade
supply in downtrends. Okay? And this is
simply going to be the same, but you're
looking to sell the market instead of
buy. All right? So, this supply and this
supply become good selling points.
Right? Let's take a look at this on a
real chart. So, we're doing a bit of
replay and we're looking at NZDPY
15minut time frame, but for reference,
this will work on any time frame you
want to approach the market from. So at
this point in time, we are looking at a
downtrend. We've seen the market here
create a high. Then we've pushed into a
lower low. Then we've created a lower
high. We've pushed again into a lower
low and a lower high. And now we've
pushed lower once again. So we are now
in a downtrending move. Right? Just to
draw that out for you. We have this kind
of price action. And we are currently
trading down here. Now we can see this
downward move, this breakup structure
was created by a supply zone here. And
to show you how I plot supply, I simply
use the last candle before the impulse
that has imbalance. So don't get
confused. I'll break it down for you.
Now we see this candle here, this gray
candle. This is the last candle before
the impulse to the downside. Okay? So
that is why that will be the supply
zone. Simply the last candle essentially
before the push begins. So to show you a
couple more examples, we would have this
gray candle here. This is the last
candle before an impulse to the downside
that broke structure. Therefore, that is
going to be the supply zone. As you can
see, if you'd have sold that supply,
you'd have caught a very nice entry to
that move. Okay. Now, the imbalance
point I just made, an imbalance is
simply an open candle range. So when we
look at, for example, the supply zone
we're currently focusing in on, we can
see the wicks of these candles here go
up to this point, but don't go into the
supply zone. So that creates basically
in this area here what we call
imbalance, right? There is no wick
filling this zone. So if this wick had
traded in, that would have created
efficiency or balance. Therefore, we
wouldn't have any imbalance. Therefore,
this supply wouldn't be of interest to
us. But because there is still this open
price range between these wicks and the
wick of the supply zone, there is
basically a draw. This is going to act
as a magnet that pulls price towards
that level. So this is therefore a level
of interest. Now that is why we are not
going to be interested in for example
this which is a last candle before an
impulse. Why is that? Well, because this
one has already been hit. So this could
have provided its own trade but we are
kind of past that point now. there is no
gap between this wick and the candle
that we're looking at as our supply.
Therefore, there's no real reason uh to
focus on that level. Okay. Again, here
we have supply, but there is no
imbalance. There was initially between
this candle and this candle, but the
markets filled this now. So, there is no
imbalance there for us to focus on.
Therefore, making this one irrelevant as
well. So the zone that we're looking at
here is basically the last imbalance
point in this leg of downward price
action, right? Nowhere imbalance down
here anymore. The only imbalance left is
up at this point. So with this being the
last candle before the impulse and with
it being an imbalanced supply zone, we
know the market is trending down. We
have that clearly mapped down,
correction, impulse, correction,
impulse, we would then want to look at
this supply zone as our selling move.
Okay? So providing we don't push above
the high around here or even in this
scenario around these points, we should
remain bearish. Therefore, we could
confidently sell this supply with stop
losses above those highs and expect the
market to at least come down towards
this low again. Right? So a simple way
to approach is simply to target the low
that's been printed in the market. Now
you can actually extend trades further
because you're protrend trading. So if
you wanted to and you expected the
market to keep going, you could extend
the target further. But for simplicity's
sake, we're going to look at it like
this and actually map just a target down
into the low. All right. So generally
then what we would expect to see is for
the market to return to the supply zone
and then lead down in an impulsive move
to create a new low which would then
open the doors to the next opportunity.
Right. Again, with this push down that
we've now seen, we could look at the
last candle before the impulse down.
That's going to be up here for this
example. So, this would be where we
would look to sell the market. All
right? So, if you were following this
simple trend trading system, you would
have your entry around this supply. Your
target would go down into the swing low
here. And then you would just look to
sell that market when the market returns
to it. Now, obviously, there are
nuances. You can use confirmations and
things like that, but we're keeping this
lesson on track on topic to market
structure. So, we're going to just
follow this simplistic approach. Market
returns to there. We are then hoping to
see the market sell off. And as you see
in this instance, it didn't happen. So,
what we get here instead is number one,
a losing trade. So, that's going to be
minus 1%. When we factor that up though,
we have a minus 1% trade here and we
have a plus 3.94% trade there. So, in
total over these two trades, you've made
2.94%
even though you've only won one and
you've lost one. Okay? 50% win rate.
You're still up 3% just over two
positions. Now, this is where the real
beauty of trend trading kicks in. Let's
think about what this has actually told
us. Although we've just lost a trade,
the market has broken structure. We've
seen a push which has created a BOS over
a previous structural high. So, let's
map that. We're up 2.94% so far. And
what we've actually done at this point
in time is reshift the structure from
down to up. So if we continue this
structure mapping, we've got one
impulse, correction, impulse,
correction, impulse, correction,
impulse. Now we've had another impulse.
Okay, so we had some internal structure
mess around and then we had a big push
to the upside which has created an
impulse. What has this impulse done?
This has given us a higher high. A
higher high indicates the market is
likely changing direction. So what do we
do from this point on? Well, first of
all, that's going to be the low that
we're focused on. If the market pushes
under this low, that would actually
shift us back into downtrend. But
providing we stay above that low, we can
actually now look for buying moves. So,
what I'm going to do here is mark out
the demand zone, which is the last
candle before the impulse, which has
created this break of structure. So,
what we would now want to do is place
our buy orders here, stop loss under the
low, and then we could target the newly
formed high. Or we could extend that
target even further because we now have
a good idea and a good understanding
that it's quite likely the market will
retake this high given that it follows
the standard trend structure of let me
just map it out. Low, lower low, lower
high, higher high, confirming trend
reversal. We're now looking for a higher
low to take us into higher highs. So,
the no-brainer trade is the one we have
mapped here. Now, let's give this a
moment and see how this goes.
So, we see internal structure. Market's
not really doing too much at the moment.
Then, we come down into this area of
demand. So, the trade is then going to
be triggered at this point. Now, you're
in a position where number one, the
market goes up and you win. Number two,
the market goes down and that's going to
reshift the trend and provide you with a
new opportunity to go the other way and
sell. Okay? So, the goal with trend
trading is not to be right all of the
time. Nothing in trading is going to
make you right all of the time. The goal
here and with pretty much every form of
trading is just to have positive
riskreward and positive expectancy.
Meaning, we can be wrong on 50 or even
60% of trades, but the ones that win are
considerably larger. So, if we take a
look at this, we've had a 5.42% win
there at 1% risk. We have 2.94% 5.42%.
We're looking at around an 8.3ish%
return over these positions. So, we have
one loss, two wins, decent win rate, but
nothing crazy, 66%. And we've actually
made 8.3% in just three positions by
using this simple supply and demand
method in line with market structure. So
it's incredibly simple, but this is how
we start to turn market structure
theories into actual trades. Now there
is an extra way that you can double
confirm trades if you feel a little bit
nervous placing sell orders and buy
orders on these supply and demand zones.
This is what we call a standard
confirmation entry. Now in this market
we can see there is a clear downtrend at
the moment. We created our low lower
high. Now we've pushed down with a
massive impulse into a new lower low.
So, if this high around here breaks,
that would push us back into an uptrend
because that would create a impulse,
which was bullish. But providing we stay
underneath this high, we would be
creating a lower high. Therefore, we'd
have good odds to sell this market down
back towards the lows. Okay? So, an
immediate trade you could do following
the uh method we just discussed would be
a short position or a sell trade. You'd
sell supply with a stop loss over the
high and your target would go down into
this low. Now, this of course is what we
just discussed. This would be a fine way
to approach the trade. However,
psychology plays an important role in
trading and some people are going to be
a bit too scared to go placing buy and
sell orders on supply and demand zones
like this. And sometimes you might have
a couple of zones that you work with and
you're not sure which one's going to be
the one that's going to create the good
move. So, this is where that standard
confirmation comes in. Okay. Now, a
standard confirmation is simply a price
structure reversal that happens on a
smaller time frame to the one that we've
prepared our idea on. And what it looks
like is this that I'm drawing on the
chart right now. We have an area where
the market is going from higher highs
and higher lows, breaks down into a
lower low, and then we just simply look
to use a supply zone up here to sell the
market when it returns to this level. we
would generally look for these patterns
inside of supply and demand zones that
we're interested in buying or selling
from. So in a sell scenario, we have our
supply zone. We know if the market gets
into here, we've got good odds of
selling. So we would then look for this
pattern on a lower time frame once the
market has hit this supply zone. And if
we see that, so essentially what we're
looking for is a movement like this,
that's going to give us the indication
and the confirmation that we need to
basically double confirm the trade and
give us maximum confidence on this
position, which gives us the benefit of
being able to execute it without
worrying. And essentially then you will
look to get in at this point at the top
of the smaller corrective move after
this lower time frame has also created a
break of structure. Now this market did
provide this opportunity. So let's take
a look at that. Now we're going to drop
down to the 5minute for this one. We are
now looking for that standard
confirmation that we just discussed once
the market has hit this level of supply.
Okay. So here you can see we've had a
push up high pull back higher low push
up higher high pullback lower low. So
here we've had a break of structure on a
lower time frame. Okay. The break came
in here when this candle closed beneath
this previous higher low. So you can see
that kind of we get a trend inside of a
trend, right? Although we're looking at
an overall downtrend, we can see that
there is kind of its own uptrend on this
lower time frame. So what we're looking
for is this uptrend to also shift into a
downtrend because then we have high time
frame and low time frame agreement.
Right? When you get high time frame and
low time frame agreement, you have the
best odds of success in a trade. Now,
what we're looking for is a supply zone
with imbalance. We can see here this
blue candle, which is the last candle
before the impulse, the last candle that
goes sideways before the push down,
right? Still has some imbalance in it
between this wick just here. Okay? So,
therefore, that's going to be our area
of interest. We can sell there, stop
above the high. Now, realistically, you
can put your stop loss above the swing
high. If you want to be safe, though,
you can still keep it over the higher
time frame structure. And then targets
wise, we are just going to go down and
target
the low that we were looking at before.
So if we go back up to the 10-minute
time frame, you can see that we also
have that confirmation here. High,
higher low, higher high, lower low.
Okay, we've had a break underneath. Now
we'd be looking to sell upon the return
to this level. So this would be a 5%
return trade. If you went for the
refined one, you're looking at 10% plus,
which is a massive position. And here's
what it looks like in the real market.
So you see a drive down from that level
and slowly slowly surely eventually the
market gets its way down to the target.
So that is how you use confirmation
entries to get safer opportunities
because number one you've got high time
frame agreement large bearish impulse
corrective move supply zone to sell. Now
number two you've got low time frame
agreement. We have the impulse on the
low time frame shifting us into a
bearish market. We can look for a
pullback and then we can sell from
there. we can target this level and we
have many opportunities to take partial
profits or go break even or stop trail
along the way. Now, we're going to talk
about substructure and swing structure
because this is where a lot of different
opportunities come in. So, remember we
discussed the impulse correction format
of a market. Well, depending on what
time frame we're looking at, we're going
to have kind of trends inside of trends.
So if your high time frame analysis and
your high time frame trend is on say the
4hour time frame on the 30inut time
frame, the hourly time frame, the
15-minut time frame, the 5minut time
frame, there are going to be these
smaller trends inside of trends. You're
going to see smaller trends taking place
as you zoom in because there are more
candlesticks available. So we can
section the analysis into two types.
Number one is the swing structure and
that is the clear directional bias of
the higher time frame that you've
analyzed. So if we analyzed an uptrend
on the 4hour, the 4hour structure is
going to be the swing structure and the
uptrend that we found there is going to
be again the swing structure. But this
is where the magic happens because
inside of the corrective moves or the
pullback moves that we see we get
substructure which is kind of that
internal structure that we discussed.
This is going to be just the corrective
pullback move. But when we look at this
on a time frame lower than the one we
analyzed on. So in this example, if we
have a 4hour as our swing structure and
it's an uptrend, then anything beneath
the 4 hour, so perhaps a 30 minute could
be our substructure. And what we're
going to see on the 30 minute there is
inside of the corrective moves, we're
going to see smaller trends.
And what we're going to see there on the
30 minute is inside of these corrective
moves, we're going to see smaller
downtrends. Okay? Whereas these might
not be so visible on the 4 hour, it
might just look like a couple of candles
pulling back. There's going to be actual
obvious trends when we scale in,
creating that trends inside of trends
format that we've just discussed. Now,
why is this beneficial? Why am I telling
you? Because this provides us with new
trades.
We don't just have to stay isolated to
buying the higher lows. But what we can
also do is look at opportunities in the
corrective moves to sell down through
the corrective move inside of these
lower time frame downtrends. Now, there
are some nuances around this and we need
to be careful that we don't try to
extend markets too far. So, what we're
going to do is go to the real charts and
I'll show you some examples of how we
can trade this substructure. Let's go
now. All right. So, for this example,
we're going to look at XAUSD, which is
gold, and we're going to the 4 hour.
We're going to do that 4hour 30 minute
format. So we can see the structure here
has just shifted from bearish with these
lower lows and lower highs into bullish
with this break of structure which
pushed us over the previous lower high.
Okay, again all of this down here is
internal structure. So the break doesn't
take place until this high goes. Now
with the market pushing into an uptrend,
our obvious next move is going to be
looking for a buy on this market when we
pull back to an imbalanced demand zone.
uh imbalanced demand zone. The lowest
possible one is going to be here. So we
would look for a position that looks
something like this. Waiting for a pull
back down to then buy higher. This is
the swing structure. Okay, the 4hour is
now officially in an uptrend. This is
the first impulse we are going to be
looking for on the 4hour time frame.
Correction, impulse, correction,
impulse, and so on and so on and so on.
However, of course, if we are expecting
this market to get lower, well, then
isn't there opportunity for us to sell
through this range? Surely there is a
trade somewhere for us in there that we
can take on a lower time frame. And that
is what this substructure trading is all
about. So, if we go down to the 30inut
time frame now, what we're going to be
looking for here is a shift in the
30-inut structure. Because as we can see
at the moment along with the 4hour the
30inut structure is also up. We're
creating higher highs and higher lows
continuously and that is still pretty
much exactly what we're doing right now.
But if there was to be a break of
structure like this, well that would
change the narrative here on this lower
time frame. We would have seen a higher
low break and that would then lead us
into the possibility of selling on this
30inut trend. And there's nothing that
really makes this 30inut trend less
valuable than the 4hour. Okay. So what
we can do here is look for opportunity
to sell the 30-inut as if it's isolated
pair and then when we start to reach
more significant swing structure areas
we should look to get out. Now what we
don't want to do is try to push a
substructure trade too far. We should
always understand if we're trading this
substructure format, we only want to
trade it down towards previous areas of
demand because we expect the market is
likely to trust the 4hour more than the
30 minute. Meaning the market is more
likely to go higher once again rather
than turning into a new downtrend. Okay,
on the higher time frame. So any
substructure trades we take essentially
should take place within the confines of
the last swing structure move. If the
swing structure move is going up, we
don't want to try and trade past that
low, but we just want to see if we can
push this market down into an area of
demand before we then start buying once
again. So essentially, we create what we
call a sell to buy scenario. We are
looking to sell here and then we are
looking to buy from there onwards. Okay,
but it provides us with new fresh
opportunity on kind of trends inside of
trends. Uh we have our big picture
narrative. Now we can look for an
opportunity inside of that.
So, here is a quick rundown of what this
might look like in a real market. We've
seen the market push down under this
level. We've then seen a pull back up.
We didn't get a closure. So, we probably
wouldn't want to immediately look for a
trade just there. Although, had we got
in there, that would have been a very
nice place to do so. Okay. So, if we'd
have seen a candle closure under this
low, this would have been the ideal
location for us to then sell from. But
what we would really want to do is see a
more significant breakdown from there.
We need to see closures under this level
essentially to validate that we are
ready to go lower. Now, yes, we did have
a break here, but with substructure
trades, it's always nice to see us
pushing more significantly into the
range so that we're not getting into
positions too soon. Because, of course,
what we don't want to do is dive into a
sell and then just get killed by the
impulse continuing. We want clear
indication that the impulsive move of
the market being this move here is over
for now and that the corrective move is
beginning. Okay. So, there's a couple
ways we could approach this. Number one,
we saw a closure under this level. So,
you could realistically enter there. You
could put your stop losses above the
next high and you could look to take the
market down towards that target where
you would then look for buys. Number
two, we can wait for the formation of a
new demand zone or supply zone and then
sell from there. So, we have a supply
zone just here.
The market went and pushed down and
closed. So, you could look at selling
from this level,
and you could look to take that down
towards your target. Now, this one's a
little bit messy. I'd prefer to go for
the first opportunity of closing under
the low and then selling into it, but
this one is okay as well.
And as you can see, the markets then
pulled back and tapped it. And now we're
looking essentially for a continuation
lower, which is what we want to see to
provide opportunity for us to be, you
know, in this position safely. Now, at
this point, we'd have got in pretty much
on that first wick. The market came
back, tapped entry one more time, and
has now pushed down to create more
significant lows. So, what you could do
at this point is just hold this trade
out and see if this is going to be the
trade that gets down towards your demand
zone on a higher time frame. So this
area from this high down to this low
becomes your substructure area and it
provides trades essentially trends
inside of trends and trades inside of
trades. You have your big picture
narrative of waiting for a corrective
move to then buy the impulsive move and
continue the swing structure. But it
actually allows you to take these
smaller trades because what we've done
here is confirm change in the trend that
then can be sold into to bring this
market lower. So that's the general idea
of how we would trade swing and
substructure. And then of course after
the substructure move is completed, your
buy limit
on the demand zone to get you into the
impulsive swing structure move is going
to be triggered leading you then back
into new highs, higher prices, and
another profitable trade. So as you can
see, this is why we don't want to try
and take substructure trades too far
because as soon as the demand zone was
hit, we just created a big move to the
upside. So any substructure trade we
take should look to pretty much just
fill some of the range. Then we want to
get out and move into the overall
substructure idea because that's the one
that's going to be the highest
confidence and the highest probability.
So there are often times opportunity to
do this. Not every piece of substructure
is going to give you a chance to get in.
I'm saying based on the price action we
saw up here, there wouldn't have been
much opportunity for me to sell this
movement back down. But a lot of the
time you are going to get opportunity to
sell down with the substructure on the
way into larger trades inside of the
swing structure move. Okay? So you look
for your short-term sells there,
long-term buys there, short-term sells
there, long-term buys there. All right?
And as you can see, we never really want
to push the market past an area of
demand. You're good to just run it down
to where you think it's going to buy
from and then you can buy and you might
find yourself a little sell on the way
into it. If you enjoyed that video, hit
the link in the description at the top.
There is a free course which is going to
help you to build a trading strategy.
Second link goes to my academy if you
really want to master this fast. And
with that said, that is it for this
class. So, thank you for watching. If
you don't want to do either of those
things, then watch this video next.
Thank you. I'll see you in the next one.